<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="alphabetic letter" n="V" org="uniform" sample="complete"><entryFree key="Vent1" type="main" opt="n"><orth extent="full" opt="n">Vent,</orth> 1) a small aperture or passage for air: <cit><quote>through little --s and crannies of the place the wind wars with his torch,</quote> <bibl n="shak. luc 310" default="NO" valid="yes">Lucr. 310</bibl></cit>. <cit><quote>this no slaughter-house no tool imparteth to make more v. for passage of her breath,</quote> <bibl n="shak. luc 310" default="NO" valid="yes">Lucr. 310</bibl></cit><lb />2) any small hole or opening made for passage: <emph>which of you will stop the v. of hearing when loud Rumour speaks,</emph> H4B Ind. <bibl n="shak. luc 310" default="NO" valid="yes">Lucr. 310</bibl> <cit><quote>how thy wounds bleed at many --s,</quote> <bibl n="shak. tro 5.3.82" default="NO" valid="yes">Troil. V, 3, 82</bibl></cit>.
<lb />3) discharge, emission: <cit><quote>here, on her breast, there is a v. of blood,</quote> <bibl n="shak. ant 5.2.352" default="NO" valid="yes">Ant. V, 2, 352</bibl></cit>.
<lb />4) utterance: <cit><quote>free v. of words love's fire doth assuage,</quote> <bibl n="shak. ven 334" default="NO" valid="yes">Ven. 334</bibl></cit>. <cit><quote>thou didst make tolerable v. of thy travels,</quote> <bibl n="shak. aww 2.3.213" default="NO" valid="yes">All's II, 3, 213</bibl></cit>.
<lb />5) freedom from restraint, liberty of indulging one's animal spirits: <emph>it</emph> (war) <cit><quote>is sprightly walking, audible, and full of v.</quote> <bibl n="shak. cor 4.5.238" default="NO" valid="yes">Cor. IV, 5, 238</bibl></cit> (according to the common interpretation, == 'full of rumour, full of materials for discourse.' If <emph>vent</emph> is, indeed, a technical term of sportsmen for scent, as it has been asserted in Edinb. Rev. Oct. 72, and if it could be proved to have been so in the time of Shakespeare, the explanation given there would be undoubtedly preferable to any other: 'when the hound vents anything, he pauses to verify the scent, and then, full of eager excitement, strains in the leash to be after the game. Full of vent, therefore, means keenly excited, full of pluck and courage').
<pb n="1313" />
</entryFree></div1></body></text></TEI.2>