<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="alphabetic letter" n="M" org="uniform" sample="complete"><entryFree key="Model" type="main" opt="n"><orth extent="full" opt="n">Model</orth> (cf. <emph>Module</emph>), 1) outline, pattern of something to be made, representation in little: <cit><quote>will it serve for any m. to build mischief on?</quote> <bibl n="shak. ado 1.3.48" default="NO" valid="yes">Ado I, 3, 48</bibl></cit>. <cit><quote>when we mean to build, we first survey the plot, then draw the m.</quote> <bibl n="shak. 2h4 1.3.42" default="NO" valid="yes">H4B I, 3, 42</bibl></cit>. <cit><quote>draw anew the m. in fewer offices,</quote> <bibl n="shak. 2h4 1.3.42" default="NO" valid="yes">H4B I, 3, 42</bibl></cit> <cit><quote>the plot of situation and the m.</quote> <bibl n="shak. 2h4 1.3.42" default="NO" valid="yes">H4B I, 3, 42</bibl></cit> <cit><quote>I'll draw the form and m. of our battle,</quote> <bibl n="shak. r3 5.3.24" default="NO" valid="yes">R3 V, 3, 24</bibl></cit>.<lb />2) any thing shaped in imitation of something greater, a copy, image: <cit><quote>thy brother, who was the m. of thy father's life,</quote> <bibl n="shak. r2 1.2.28" default="NO" valid="yes">R2 I, 2, 28</bibl></cit>; cf. <cit><quote>the m. of our chaste love, his young daughter,</quote> <bibl n="shak. h8 4.2.132" default="NO" valid="yes">H8 IV, 2, 132</bibl></cit>; <cit><quote>princes are a m., which heaven makes like to itself,</quote> <bibl n="shak. per 2.2.11" default="NO" valid="yes">Per. II, 2, 11</bibl></cit>. <cit><quote>that small m. of the barren earth which serves as paste and cover to our bones,</quote> <bibl n="shak. r2 3.2.153" default="NO" valid="yes">R2 III, 2, 153</bibl></cit> (the grave, which, to the dead, represents the whole earth. "According to Malone, the king means to say that the earth placed upon the body assumes its form; according to Douce, model seems to mean in this place a measure, portion, or quantity." Dyce. cf. besides <emph>mould</emph> in Edward III, A. V, Sc. 3: <emph>the pillars of his herse shall be their bones; the mould that covers him, their cities' ashes</emph>). <cit><quote>showing, as in a m., our firm estate,</quote> <bibl n="shak. r2 3.4.42" default="NO" valid="yes">R2 III, 4, 42</bibl></cit>. <cit><quote>thou, the m. where old Troy did stand,</quote> <bibl n="shak. r2 5.1.11" default="NO" valid="yes">V, 1, 11</bibl></cit>. <cit><quote>O England, m. to thy inward greatness, like little body with a mighty heart,</quote> <bibl n="shak. h5 2.0" default="NO" valid="yes">H5 II Chor.</bibl></cit> <bibl n="shak. h5 2.0" default="NO" valid="yes">H5 II Chor.</bibl>*<cit><quote>my father's signet, which was the m. of that Danish seal,</quote> <bibl n="shak. ham 5.2.50" default="NO" valid="yes">Hml. V, 2, 50</bibl></cit>.
</entryFree></div1></body></text></TEI.2>